AISHWARYA VENKAT

+1 (202) 651-0979 | aishwarya.venkat@tufts.edu | aish-venkat.github.io | LinkedIn

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Experienced researcher and geospatial analyst studying food systems resilience and climate-food-health nexus. Strengths include spatiotemporal alignment and data wrangling in Python and R to extract novel interdisciplinary insights. Subject matter expertise in food security and agriculture, acute malnutrition seasonality, diet costs and affordability, early warning systems, extreme weather measurement, disaster risk reduction, and risk information systems.

EDUCATION

Friedman School of Nutrition Science and Policy, Tufts University

May 2024

PhD, Agriculture, Food, and Environment

Dissertation: Climate and Health: Extreme Events, Food Systems, and Nutrition

School of Engineering, Tufts University

May 2018

MS, Environmental and Water Resources Engineering Certificate in Water Systems, Science, and Society *Thesis*: Sub-Basin Valuation of Groundwater in California, 2000-2016

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (Virginia Tech)

May 2014

BS, Biological Systems Engineering Secondary Major Certificate, French

SKILLS

Spatial analysis: Python, R; ArcGIS, QGIS, Geoda, Google Earth Engine; Mapbox, Carto Statistical analysis and data visualization: R, Python, Stata; Excel, Power BI, Tableau Languages: English (fluent), French (advanced), Tamil (advanced), Hindi (advanced) Other: Activity management, training, critical thinking, interdisciplinary communication

EXPERIENCE

GIS Consultant, iDE Global

October 2024

Developed ArcGIS web app with subnational administrative, demographic, and health data in six countries for the Transforming Lives through Nutrition project Established a GIS implementation roadmap with geolocated programs and activities

Research Fellow, Project Drawdown

September 2024 - Present

Reviewed literature for a suite of emissions reduction solutions in the AFOLU sector Extracted measures of current and potential adoption, costs, and reduction potential Developed workflows and visualizations to quantify interactions between solutions

Consultant, The Micronutrient Forum

2023-2023

Developed and drafted literature review of climate hazard measurement in nutrition Performed analysis of extreme weather events and stunting and wasting outcomes

Research Assistant, Food Prices for Nutrition Research Group at Tufts University 2020-2022

Conducted comparison of least-cost diets using WB ICP data and 11 dietary guidelines Contributed analysis and evaluation of Cost of Healthy Diet metric for SOFI 2020-2022 Developed technical tools to facilitate calculation of Cost of Healthy Diet

Research Assistant, Feinstein International Center at Tufts University

2018-2020

Conducted analysis of anthropometric and climatological data to contextualize acute malnutrition trends in Kenyan drylands

Performed study of short-term (1990-present) and long-term (1900-present) seasonal patterns of climatic indicators in the Darfur region and links to farmer-herder violence

Research Assistant, Center for Humanitarian Change

2019-2019

Studied alignment of Integrated Phase Classification (IPC) and Household Hunger Scale (HHS) in SMART contexts with survey data from 336 households

GIS Lab Assistant, Data Lab at Tufts University

2014-2018

Assisted students and faculty with geospatial projects; created and updated metadata Designed and led *Intro to QGIS* and *Mapping Open Data in R* workshops

EcoHealthNet Research Exchange, EcoHealth Alliance

Summer 2017

Collected data on commercial poultry production and live markets in seven countries for the *African Sustainable Livestock* 2050 project

Generated network diffusion models from World Bank LSMS and USAID DHS surveys Identified continental drivers of emerging infectious diseases using geostatistical models

Analysis Intern & Consultant, International Water Management Institute

2016-2017

Evaluated target and actual progress across all WLE programs in 2015 and 2016 Mapped impact pathways and identified evidence gaps Documented activities, goals, and targets for the 2015 and 2016 WLE Annual Reports

Water Program Intern, Ceres Inc.

Fall 2015

Analyzed CDP disclosures from food and beverage companies to document emissions targets, progress, and achievement strategies

Developed data analyses and visualizations related to California drought

Research Assistant, AidData at the College of William and Mary

Summer 2015

Harmonized climate and demographic covariates for geospatial impact evaluation of indigenous lands project in the Brazilian Amazon

Independent Consultant

Spring 2015

Implemented vulnerability analysis to identify communities with low supply and high demand of basic human services in Jalisco, Mexico

GIS Intern, City of Medford, Massachusetts

Spring 2015

Updated stormwater and sewer geodatabases and developed work maps Identified homes and infrastructure vulnerable to floods based on FEMA Flood Maps

Research Assistant, WASH Advocates

Summer 2014

Matched areas of highest cholera incidence with responders in Haiti and DR Compiled congressional briefs, contributed to H.R. 2901 Water for the World Act

Intern, Meals on Wheels Association of America

Summer 2014

Documented farmers markets accepting SNAP/EBT benefits in Virginia Supported research and advocacy efforts around nutrition programs for elderly

TEACHING ACTIVITIES AND ASSISTANTSHIPS

- UEP 294: Spatial Statistics, Tufts University (Spring 2019)
- Tufts University GIS Data Lab Assistant (Fall 2014 Spring 2018)
- EN 1: Applications of Climate Change Engineering, Tufts University (Fall 2016)
- CEE 194: Intro to GIS, Tufts University (Summer 2016)
- ENVR-S 171: Water, Health and Sustainable Development, Harvard University Extension School (Spring and Summer 2016)

HONORS AND AWARDS

Outstanding Recent Alumni, Virginia Tech College of Agriculture and Life Sciences 2020 N. Bruce and Lorry Hanes Endowed Fellowship 2016 United States Geospatial Intelligence Foundation Scholarship 2015 J. Lawrence & Lucille G. Calhoun Scholarship, 2013

PUBLICATIONS

Headey, D., and **Venkat**, **A**. (2024). Extreme weather and undernutrition: A critical but constructive review of the literature. IFPRI Discussion Paper 02236. Washington, DC: International Food Policy Research Institute.

Maxwell, D., Adan, G., Hailey, P., Day, M., Odhaimbo, S. B. J., Kaindi, L., Njiru, J., **Venkat, A.**, & Marshak, A. (2023). <u>Using the household hunger scale to improve analysis and classification of severe food insecurity in famine-risk conditions: Evidence from three countries</u>. *Food Policy*, 118: 102449.

Venkat, A., Marshak, A., Young, H., & Naumova, E.N (2023). <u>Seasonality of Acute Malnutrition in African Drylands: Evidence From 15 Years of SMART Surveys</u>. Food and Nutrition Bulletin. 44(2_suppl):S94-S108. doi:10.1177/03795721231178344.

Cliffer, I.R., Marshak, A., Schneider, K.R., **Venkat, A.**, & Naumova, E.N. (2023). <u>Seasonality of nutrition</u>. In: Caballero, B. (Ed.), Encyclopedia of Human Nutrition, vol. 4. Elsevier, Academic Press, pp. 350–368.

Herforth, A., **Venkat**, A., Bai, Y., Costlow, L., Holleman, C. & Masters, W.A. (2022). <u>Methods and options to monitor the cost and affordability of a healthy diet globally. Background paper for The State of Food Security and Nutrition in the World 2022. FAO Agricultural Development Economics Working Paper 22-03. Rome, FAO.</u>

Marshak, A., **Venkat**, A., Young, H., & Naumova, E. N. (2021). <u>How seasonality of malnutrition is measured and analyzed</u>. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 18(4), 1828.

Herforth, A., Bai, Y., **Venkat, A.**, Mahrt, K., Ebel, A., & Masters, W. A. (2020). <u>Cost and affordability of healthy diets across and within countries: Background paper for The State of Food Security and Nutrition in the World 2020. FAO Agricultural Development Economics Technical Study (Vol. 9). Food and Agriculture Organization.</u>

FAO and Tufts University [Young, H., Marshak, A., & Venkat, A.]. (2019). <u>Twin peaks: the seasonality of acute malnutrition, conflict and environmental factors – Chad, South Sudan and the Sudan</u>. September 2019. Rome.

Venkat, A., Falconi, T. M. A., Cruz, M., Hartwick, M. A., Anandan, S., Kumar, N., Ward, H., Balaji, V., & Naumova, E. N. (2019). <u>Spatiotemporal Patterns of Cholera Hospitalization in Vellore, India</u>. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 16(21), 4257.

Simpson, R. B., **Venkat**, **A**., Alarcon, T., Chui, K., Naumov, Y., Gorski, J., Bhattacharyya, S. & Naumova, E. (2019). <u>Calendar effects to forecast influenza seasonality: A case study in Milwaukee, WI</u>. Online Journal of Public Health Informatics, 11(1).

Venkat, A. (2018). <u>Sub-basin Valuation of Agriculture: A Crop-specific Assessment of Groundwater Footprints and Value in California</u>. (Master of Science dissertation, Tufts University).

Cruz, M. S., Alarcon-Falconi, T. M., Hartwick, M. A., **Venkat, A.**, Ehrlich, H. Y., Anandan, S., & Naumova, E. N. (2017). <u>From hospitalization records to surveillance: The use of local patient profiles to characterize cholera in Vellore, India. PloS one, 12(8), e0182642.</u>

Gobierno del Estado de Jalisco [González, A. C. A., **Venkat, A.**, Jiménez, A. M. T., de Oca, Á. M. M.]. (2014). Estudio de identificación de las áreas de intervención estratégica que contribuyan a superar la pobreza en Jalisco. México.